Guide to the Yale-New Haven Hospital Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Yale-New Haven Hospital records
1904-1977
MS 835
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
6.75
(9 boxes)
The records consist of the administrative records of the Yale-New Haven Hospital from the office of the Executive Director. A large part of the records are from the office of Albert W. Snoke who was executive Director from 1946-1968. The records cover the history of the hospital as a whole and its individual departments, its relations with Yale University, the city of New Haven, the state of Connecticut, and general issues such as health care delivery, voluntary health organizations, internships, family planning, and establishment of regional programs. Included are correspondence, oral histories, reports, clippings, memoranda, minutes of meetings, legal and financial records, and speeches. These papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Yale-New Haven Hospital
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Albert Snoke Papers (Papers of the Executive Director, Yale-New Haven Hospital) Received from Albert Snoke, 7/20/1978; transferred fom the Yale University Medical Library, 1979.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of the administrative records of the Yale-New Haven Hospital from the office of the Executive Director. A large part of the records are from the office of Albert W. Snoke who was executive Director from 1946-1968. The records cover the history of the hospital as a whole and its individual departments, its relations with Yale University, the city of New Haven, the state of Connecticut, and general issues such as health care delivery, voluntary health organizations, internships, family planning, and establishment of regional programs. Included are correspondence, oral histories, reports, clippings, memoranda, minutes of meetings, legal and financial records, and speeches.
Any of the files may contain correspondence, minutes of meetings, memoranda, reports, program outlines, and notes. In some places it appears that Snoke has also added materials from his personal files. (Materials dated after ca. 1967 could not have been created by Snoke as the hospital's executive director.) Snoke has apparently made a very careful selection from the files that were stored at the hospital and has included here only those files which will document what he considered to be the important issues or developments in health care during his tenure. Snoke has arranged these selected files according to a topical scheme. The files are now grouped under seven general headings: Hospital Activities and History; Hospital Departments; Yale University, which I understand as meaning the relationship between the hospital and the University; City of New Haven, which concerns the hospital's relationship to city government; State of Connecticut, which includes materials on coordinating the development of health care facilities statewide and dealings with the state government; National, which deals with some issues involving the federal government but also covers national medical organizations; and Miscellaneous. Material on any particular subject can be found under more than one heading.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by accession.
Birth control; Family policy; Hospitals -- Administration; Hospitals -- Connecticut -- New Haven; Interns (Medicine); Malpractice; Medicine; Public health; Voluntary health agencies; Connecticut -- Politics and government; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Snoke, Albert W. (Albert Waldo), 1907-; Yale University -- Officals and employees; Yale University. School of Medicine; Yale-New Haven Hospital
- Inventory
  - Hospital Activities and History
    - Chaplaincy, 1953-1958
      - "Churches and Chaplaincy" (Box 1)
      - "Churches, New Haven Council of" (Box 1)
    - Clinical Research Centers, 1961-1966 (Box 1)
    - D. Spencer Berger Addresses, 1961-1966 (Box 1)
    - Family Planning (Birth Control), 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - Grace-New Haven School of Nursing, 1957-1967 (Box 1)
    - Hospital Financing, Cost and Reimbursement: "Hospital Finances and Operation,", 1940, 1951-1961, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Hospital Planning, 1949-1967 (Box 1)
    - Hospital Property Purchase (folder missing): "Purchase of Hospital Property,", 1957 (Box 1)
    - Malpractice Insurance: "Insurance, Malpractice,", 1955, 1959-1965 (Box 1)
    - Memorial Unit Chapel: "Chapel,", 1952-1956 (Box 1)
    - New Haven Area Hospital Planning, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
    - Paint and Clay Club: "New Haven Paint & Clay Club,", 1956-1959 (Box 1)
    - Parking, 1960-1966 (Box 1)
    - Poison Center: "Conn. Dept. of Health Information Center,", 1956-1958 (Box 1)
    - Prepared Childbirth: "Yale School of Nursing Prepared Childbirth,", 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    - Redevelopment, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
    - Regional Laundry, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
    - Rooming-in, 1952-1955 (Box 1)
    - Teenaged Unwed Mothers: "Teenage Unwed Parents Program,", 1966-1967 (Box 1)
    - Therapeutic Abortion: "Obs.-Gyn. Therapeutic Abortions,", 1964-1967 (Box 1)
    - Union, 1947, 1959-1965
      - "Labor Unions" (Box 1)
      - "Union 1947 (Maintenance Department)" (Box 1)
    - United Way: "United Fund of Greater New Haven,", 1954-1959 (Box 1)
    - University of Connecticut School of Nursing, 1954-1967 (Box 1)
    - Visiting Nursing Association-Home Health Care: "V.N.A. Home Health Care Program,", 1955-1959, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Wiggin & Dana, 1962, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Medical Staff -- Organization, Relationships and Bylaws, 1959-1966
      - Staff selection, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
    - Administrative Organization -- Yale-New Haven Hospital, 1955-1966 (Box 1)
    - "Yale-New Haven Medical Center", 1961-1962 (Box 1A)
      Scope and Contents
      A preliminary report providing the architectural program and preliminary design for expansion of the Yale-New Haven Medical Center over several decades.
    - Yale-New Haven Hospital History
      - Ancient history: "Development Committee Correspondence re: Campaign for Funds,", 1930-1940 (Box 2)
        General note
        This material was created prior to Snoke, perhaps by James A. Hamilton.
      - Past history: "Reports on Hospital Surveys of N.H. Hosp.,", 1905-1967 (Box 2)
        Most of this material was created prior to Snoke. It includes some early leaflets which are quite interesting.
      - The General Hospital Society of Connecticut, 1904-1945 (Box 2)
        Includes copy of the charter and by-laws.
      - Merger of the New Haven Hospital and the Grace Hospital (2 folders), 1945, 1946-1952 (Box 2)
        - Folder 1: "Grace-New Haven Community Hosp. Memo of Agreement"
          Note by Snoke says that this material was collected by Dr. Bishop for writing his history.
        - Folder 2: "Grace-New Haven Community Hospital - First Meetings to Consolidate"
  - Hospital Departments
    - Ambulatory Services, 1961-1967
      - "Dr. E. Richard Weinerman" Concerns search for chief, 1961 (Box 2)
        Folder contains handwritten synopsis.
        See also: Misc.
    - Anesthesia: "Anesthesia, N.M. Greene, M.D.,", 1955-1967 (Box 2)
    - Cardio-vascular Surgery, 1960-1963 (Box 2)
    - Clinical Laboratories, 1952-1965
      - "Laboratories, David Seligson, M.D." (Box 2)
      - "Laboratories, School of Medical Technology" (Box 2)
    - Dentistry: "Chief of Dental Services Herbert R. Sleeper, D.D.S.,", 1958-1967 (Box 2)
    - Dermatology, 1955-1962 (Box 2)
    - Inhalation Therapy, [1955], 1954-1962, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Opthamology: "Chief of Opthamology - Dr. M.L. Sears,", 1961-1967 (Box 2)
    - Pathology, 1951-1965 (Box 2)
    - Podiatry: "Medical Staff Podiatrists,", 1958-1965 (Box 2)
    - Psychiatry-Tompkins I: "Tompkins-I" inpatient psychiatric unit, 1957-1967 (Box 2)
    - Radio-Isotopes, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Radiology: "Radiology (Dr. Klingman),", 1955-1959 (Box 2)
    - Radio-Therapy: "Radiotherapy Patient Service,", 1963-1966 (Box 2)
    - Rehabilitation and Physical Medicine: "Rehab. Med. & Cont. Care - Harold N. Willard, M.D., Dir.,", 1965-1967 (Box 2)
    - Physical Medicine (no folder; combined with Rehabilitation)
      General
      See: Rehabilitation and Physical Medicine
    - Social Service, 1960-1965 (Box 2)
  - Yale University
    - Epidemiology and Public Health, Hospital Administration, 1946-1967 (Box 3)
    - "Emergency Care,", 1961, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - Fund Raising - Medical Center: "Fund-Raising, Federated Program,", 1964-1967 (Box 3)
    - Yale-Hospital Relations
      - 1826-1940 (Box 3)
      - 1946-1952 (Box 3)
      - 1952 - 1967 (Box 3)
    - Yale-Hospital Contract Relations (Box 3)
    - Yale-Hospital Financial Relations, 1940-1945 (Box 3)
      - "Treasurer's Office" (Box 3)
      - "Grace Consolidation with N.H. Hospital 1944 joint Comm. Yale Univ. - New Haven Hosp." (Box 3)
    - Yale-Hospital Financial Relations: "Medical School Financial Grant from Yale,", 1953-1963 (Box 3)
    - Yale-Hospital Financial Relations, donated services, 1951-1953 (Box 3)
      - "Medical School Donated Services" (Box 3)
      - Reimbursement for Third-Party and Donated Services--Yale (Box 3)
    - Yale-New Haven Medical Center and the Joint Administrative Committee, 1962-1966 (Box 3)
    - Yale University School of Nursing, 1956, 1967, 1977 (Box 3)
  - City of New Haven
    - Correspondence between the city and the hospital: "City of New Haven, Negotiations with the City,", 1952-1959 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence between the city and the hospital: "City of New Haven Welfare Department,", 1960-1966 (Box 3)
    - Department of Health, 1962-1964 (Box 3)
    - Isolation Pavilion: "New Haven, City of, Isolation Pavilion, Negotiations with the City,", 1928, 1947-1961 (Box 3)
    - Mayor Lee: "Mayor Richard C. Lee,", 1962-1965 (Box 3)
    - Reimbursement correspondence: "City of New Haven Out-Patient Reimbursement,", 1949 - (1955-1961) (Box 3)
  - State of Connecticut
    - Connecticut Blue Cross: "Blue Cross (Conn. Blue Cross Rel. to Blue Cross Commiss.),", 1950-1960 (Box 4)
    - Connecticut Hospital Planning: "Regional Hospital Planning,", 1959-1966 (Box 4)
    - Connecticut Mental Retardation: "State of Connecticut Mental Retardation Program,", 1957-1959 (Box 4)
    - Connecticut State Health Policy, 1972-1975 (Box 4)
    - Connecticut State Medical Society, 1959-1965 (Box 4)
    - Connecticut State Reimbursement: "Conn. State of - Out-Patient State Reimbursement,", 1951-1967 (Box 4)
    - Health Care Centers, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Health Planning and Organization - New Haven Health Care, Inc., 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Hill-Burton in Connecticut: "Special Priority for Hill-Harris Grant,", 1963-1967 (Box 4)
    - Hospitals--Ambulances--Department of Mental Health: "Ambulance Payment,", 1958 (Box 4)
    - Hospital Cost Commission, 1952 - (1960-1967) (Box 4)
    - Institute of Health--specific efforts in Connecticut (Box 4)
      Empty folder, see Snoke's handwritten note attached to this list.
    - Long Term Care Facilities: "Convalescent Hospitals,", 1962-1964 (Box 4)
    - Regional Connecticut Mental Health Center (two folders), 1960-1962, 1952 (Box 4)
      - Folder 1: "Conn. State of - Governor's Report on Mental Health,", 1952-1953 (Box 4)
      - Folder 2: "Connecticut Mental Health Advisory Board,", 1959-1967 (Box 4)
    - Regionalization and previous history, 1975-1976 (Box 4)
    - Reorganization Connecticut State Governmental Structure: "Personnel Health Center,", 1930-1977 (Box 4)
      Empty folder, see Snoke's handwritten note attached.
    - Rheumatic Heart Disease Program, 1949, 1951, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
      - "Conn. State Dept. of Health - Rheumatic Fever Training" (Box 4)
        Snoke wrote on the original folder: "Throw away - or keep as a record of frustration of dealing between state health depts. & a vol. hosp. 1959 & 1960"
    - University of Connecticut Medical School: "Hartford Medical School,", 1960-1962 (Box 4)
  - National
    - Connecticut Regional Medical Program (2 folders), 1965-1967, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Health Care Delivery--A Blueprint for Change (article by Snoke, handwritten note on folder "State Admin. & Organization for Health and SS Monograph Correspondence,", 1974 (Box 5)
    - Kerr-Mills, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - Mandatory Serology, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Organization of State Governments - Human or Health Services (AHS and the Council of State Governments): "AHS - State Project,", 1975 (Box 5)
    - Statewide Voluntary Health Organizations, 1974, 1976 (Box 5)
    - Straight Internship Battle: "AMA Straight Internship Battle,", 1957 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaeous
    - Personalities
      - Bernard Brody, 1951-1966 (Box 5)
        Original folder marked "Confidential." Brody, a hospital neurosurgeon, now deceased, was under the care of a psychiatrist.
      - E. Richard Weinerman, 1961 (Box 5)
        Original folder marked "Confidential." Concerned with the references for ERW before hiring by Yale. There were accusations about his politics.
        See also: Snoke memo 1977 Apr 12 in Snoke donor file.
    - Private Physicians' Offices in the Medical Center
      - Memorial Unit: "Doctors' Offices,", 1961-1967 (Box 5)
      - Medical Center Planning: "Hospital Planning,", 1949, 1959-1961 (Box 5)
    - Professional Fees
      - Resident Staff Professional Fees: "Surgery - Dental Surgery,", 1949-1965 (Box 5)
      - CMS and payment for ambulatory radiology services: "Conn. Med. Service, Inc. Radiology Coverage,", 1953, 1959-1964 (Box 5)
- Additional material, Accession 1979-M-006; 0.25; (1 box)
  - Fund-raising, Yale University (Office of Program Development), 1957-1967 (Box 1)
  - University of Connecticut Medical School, 1949 (Box 1)
  - University of Connecticut Nursing School, 1967 (Box 1)
  - School of Nursing, Yale University, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Ambulatory services, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Reimbursement, New Haven, Circa 1960 (Box 1)
  - Yale-New Haven merger, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Reimbursement, Connecticut, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Hospital financing, 1961-1966 (Box 1)
  - Hospital planning, 1948-1966 (Box 1)
  - Yale-Hospital relations, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
  - Ambulances, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Radiotherapy, 1959-1965 (Box 1)
  - Chaplaincy, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Resident staff professional fee, 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Social science, 1961-1963 (Box 1)
  - Dentistry, 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Pathology, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Anesthesiology, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Laboratories, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - City of New Haven, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Neighborhood Health Centers, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Connecticut hospital planning, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Joint administrative committee, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Printed material, 1941-1978, undated (Box 1)
- Additional material, Accession 1980-M-003; .75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Received from: Arthur Viseltear 9/18/79
  Materials: 1959-1979
  - Correspondence
    - Yale Hospital
      - Medical records, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Pediatrics, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Professional relations, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Residential staff, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Service classifications, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Yale Hospital and Medical School, financial relations, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Yale Medical School, philosophy, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Joint Commission on Hospital Accreditation, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Oral History notes; Snoke, A.W.
    - Consultations, reports and records, list, 1979 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Notes summarizing contents of Yale Hospitalfiles, K-typescripts, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notes summarizing contents of Yale Hospital files: personalities, private physician's offices, professional fees, typescripts, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Commentary on hospital departments, typescripts, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Commentary on hospital activities, typescripts, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Hospital-physician relationships, list and summaries (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Health planning and organization - New Haven Health Care, Inc., 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Institute of Health-specific effort in Connecticut and past history, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Regionalization (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Health Care Delivery- A Blueprint for changes, 1974, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Public Health Program, alumni address cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 15-17)